Guide to the Jim Cullum Collection ARS036
Archive of Recorded Sound
Jim Cullum Collection
1942-2007
Bulk, 1961-1971
ARS0036
Cullum, Jim
35 boxes: open reel tapes, audiocassettes, videocassettes, eight tracks, phonograph records, compact discs, etc.
Archive of Recorded Sound
The Happy Jazz Band was formed in 1962 by Jim Cullum with his son, Jim Cullum, Jr. in San Antonio, Texas. Devoted to jazz from between the World Wars, the Happy Jazz Band was perhaps the foremost exponent of Dixieland in the Southwest. Jim Cullum, Jr. continued the band after his father passed as the Jim Cullum Jazz Band. The Jim Cullum collection consists of tape recordings of the Happy Jazz Band and the Jim Cullum Jazz Band and covers over thirty years of the band's performances. In addition, the collection contains performances by other noteworthy performers including Jack Teagarden and Bobby Hackett, as well as lesser known, but important jazz musicians from Texas, such as cornetist Garner Clark.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Source
The Jim Cullum Collection was donated to the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound by Jim Cullum, Jr. in 2008.
Scope and Contents
The Jim Cullum Collection consists of audio and video recordings of traditional jazz revivalism in Texas. In 1962 Jim Cullum, Sr., who had played clarinet professionally with Jack Teagarden, Jimmy Dorsey, Adrian Rollini and others in the 1930s and 40s, formed a seven-piece traditional jazz group in San Antonio, Texas with his son, Jim Cullum, Jr. on cornet, called the Happy Jazz Band. After the senior Cullum's passing in 1973, the band continued under Jim's leadership as the Jim Cullum Jazz Band. The group still plays today, and the collection contains compact discs and a DVD of recent recordings.
Among the thousand-plus tapes in the collection, Cullum chose to have digitally transferred certain reels he felt were of the highest priority, highlighting undersung regional players such as cornetist (and family friend) Garner Clark and pianists Peck Kelley and Son Harrell. In order to get a better sense of the collection's contents, these transferred tapes are listed below. Other lesser known groups represented in the collection include the Bourbon Street Bums, the Dixie Ramblers, the Rubber City Retreads, the Crawford-Ferguson Night Owls, and Johnny Wigs and Bayou Stompers. More familiar musicians, such as Jack Teagarden, Bobby Hackett, Baby Dodds, Turk Murphy, and Knocky Parker, are also present.
A substantial portion of the collection belongs to performances by the Happy Jazz Band, including tape masters, live recordings, and radio broadcasts on WOAI and WWL (many of which are remotes from The Landing, a San Antonio club which has hosted their residency since they began). There are also interviews, including the Cullums on Voice of America in 1969, commercial releases (almost all Happy Jazz and the JCJB), and dubbed copies of commercial releases. There is a paper contents listing available at the Archive.
Transferred tapes
Selected tapes digitized by request of donor: Harold Duke Dejan's Olympia Brass Band: Explanation of Funeral Procession, etc. 1971; Son Harrell: Blues, Sweet Lorraine; Bobby Hackett: Marko Piano Solo, Riverboat Shuffle, Shreveport Stomp, Winin' Boy 1972; Hackett: Westmoreland Weave, Everybody Loves My Baby, etc. 1972; Garner Clark no. 2; Son Harrell: Sweet Loraine; Peck Kelly: You Took Advantage of Me, Body and Soul; Garner Clark: How Come You Do Me, Angry, If I could Be with You 1953; Hackett: Live at the Landing; Smile, Loss Butterfly, etc. 1972; Curtis Hurn; Happy Jazz Band Rehearsal for record 1963; Jim Cullum Jazz Band Central City, Colo. 1981; Terrace and Jim Cullum's Happy Jazz Band 1962; Garner Clark no. 22: Wolverine Blues, Basin St. Blues 1953; Garner Clark no. 26: Tin Roof Blues, Jazz Me Blues, Royal Garden Blues 1951; Happy Jazz Band & Paul Crawford: San Antonio Jazz Society 1962; Garner Clark with Chuck Carroll and James: White Rock Terrace 1953; Hackett: Memphis Blues 1972; Hackett 1972; Hackett, Kevin Hess, Speed, Pryor, Mark 1972; Hackett and Happy Jazz Band: Strutting with Some Barbecue, New Orleans, etc. 1972; Garner Clark and Terrance; Happy Jazz Band on Shadow Land 1962; Son Harrell: Who's Sorry Now, When A Woman Loves a Man; Happy Jazz Band; WOAI Live from the Landing 1964; Garner Clark no. 21: Muskrat Ramble, Peg o' My Heart, Milenburg Joys 1953; Garner Clark no. 25: Jada, Ballin' the Jack, Da Da Strain 1951; Curtis Hurt, Jim Cullum, CWR, Cliff Brewtin, Bob McClender; Don Albert Recalls Music Of New Orleans - Southwest Jazz Foundation 1961; Curtis Hurt, Garner Clark, Jim Cullum Sr., etc.: Put your Arms Around Me, Jazz Me Blues, etc.; Garner Clark no. 4: Sister Kate, Black and Blue, I Want to Be Happy, etc. 1953; Garner Clark no. 6: Wolverine Blues, Basin St. Blues, I Found a New Baby, etc. 1951; Garner Clark no. 15: Ballin' the Jack, Ain't She Sweet, Jazz Band Ball 1953; Garner Clark and Mel Torme: Tin Roof Blues, Boogie in C, etc. 1953; White Rock Terrace 1962; Bonnie and Geo. C. 1966; Mike Wallace Show; Garner Clark no. 28 at the VFW, Dallas: Fidgety Feet 1951; Jesse James, Jim Cullum Sr., Cliff Brewton, etc.: China Bay and Shine from Record no. 2 1942; Teagarden: Dallas Jam Session.
Indexing Terms
Cullum, Jim, Sr.; Cullum, Jim; Happy Jazz Band.; Jim Cullum Jazz Band.; Dixieland music; Jazz; Texas
- 1. Open Reel Tape, 27 boxes
  - 1-38, 38 7" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  - 39-74, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 2)
  - 75-111, 37 7" open reel tapes (Audio 3)
  - 112-148, 37 7" open reel tapes (Audio 4)
  - 149-185, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 5)
  - 186-223, 37 7" open reel tapes (Audio 6)
  - 224-259, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 7)
  - 260-295, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 8)
  - 296-332, 37 7" open reel tapes (Audio 9)
  - 333-369, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 10)
  - 371-406, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 11)
  - 543-561, 19 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 17)
  - 488-506, 19 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 14)
  - 407-442, 36 7" open reel tapes (Audio 12)
  - 443-485, 38 open reel tapes three 3"; five 4"; eighteen 5"; seventeen 7" (Audio 13)
  - 507-525, 19 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 15)
  - 525-542, 18 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 16)
  - 562-567, 570, 595, 600-610, 18 open reel tapes: ten 7"; seven 10.5"; one 2" master (Audio 18)
  - 611-648, 38 open reel tapes: one 5"; thirty-seven 7" (Audio 19)
  - 649-683, 37 open reel tapes: four 5"; thirty-three 7" (Audio 20)
  - 684-724, 42 open reel tapes: five 3"; one 5"; thirty-six 7" (Audio 21)
  - 725-741, 17 open reel tapes: five 7"; seven 10.5"; four 1/2" masters, one 2" master (Audio 22)
  - 742-780, 39 mixed media: thirty-six 7" open reel tapes; three 8 tracks (two sample/test releases, one commercial release by Cullum) (Audio 23)
  - 782-792, 11 open reel tapes: six 10.5"; two 1/2" masters; three 2" masters (Audio 24)
  - 793-798, 826, 828-832, 835-838, 1020-1042, 37 open reel tapes: one 3"; four 5"; thirty-two 7" (Audio 26)
  - 1046-1072, 1091-1092, 1107-1113, 1124, 1126 (in Box 36) 1132-1134, 44 open reel tapes: one 5"; forty-two 7"; one 10.5" (Audio 32, Box 36)
  - 1023-1024, 1078, 1093, 1096-1100, 1102, 1105, 13 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 34)
- 2. Audiocassettes, 6 boxes
  - 816, 844-878, 36 audiocassettes (Audio 27)
  - 879-914, 36 audiocassettes (Audio 28)
  - 915-937, 36 audiocassettes (Audio 29)
  - 938-974, 38 audiocassettes (Audio 30)
  - 974-1007, 36 audiocassettes (Audio 31)
  - 1008-1017, 1072-1078, 1114, 17 mixed media: sixteen audiocassettes, one DAT (Audio 33)
- 3. Video, 1 box
  - 799-825, 833-834, 1115-1119, 34 videocassettes: thirty-three VHS; one U-Matic (Box 25)
- 4. Discs
  - 1019, 1021, 1028, 1084, 1086, 1088, 1090, 1129-1131, 10 vinyl discs: 7" 45 rpm (Audio 35)
  - Instantaneous discs, 13 instantaneous discs: six 10"; seven 12" (Box 36)
    Scope and Contents
    10" discs: The Chordsmen and Happy Jazz Band (Mastersound, San Antonio); Charlie Carl- Big Fat Mama/Woodchopper (Duodisc); Hindustan/Struttin' with Some B (Audio Devices); New Orleans/Swanee (Audio Devices); Bugle Call Rag/Stumbling (Audio Devices); Dee Bell (Music City Recorders
    12" discs: I Found a New Baby/It Had to be You, Roses of Arcady (RCA); Isle of Capri/Song of the Islands (Sound Recording Studios, Dallas); I Can't Give You Anything but Love/No. 50 Blues (Sound Recording Studios, Dallas); 2 unlabeled Presto; Moonlight on the Ganges/Blue Lou, The Sheik (RCA); Georgia/Sweet Lorraine (RCA)
  - Happy Jazz Band (Happy Jazz Records AP-87) [no cover]; three white-label test pressings, 4 12" vinyl discs (Box 36)
- 5. Optical media, 8 mixed media: seven compact discs; one DVD (Box 25)
  Seven unnumbered compact disc recordings of the Jim Cullum Jazz Band including Riverwalk Live from the Landing CD series RW CD-1, 3-6, 8-9, and one DVD recording of 2007 Concert Highlights.
- 6. Notes on recordings (photocopies, inserts from tape boxes, etc.), 12 folders (Box 35)